Hi, I’m Olivier.
Welcome to Oxford Online English!
In this lesson, you can learn about
sentence structure in English.
You’ll learn how to construct all kinds
of sentences in English, from the
simplest.
Possible sentences, to long, complex
sentences which contain many different
ideas.
To begin, a question:.
What is the simplest sentence you can
make in English?
What does every sentence in English need?
Every sentence needs a verb.
The simplest sentence is an imperative,
which means when you tell someone to do
something.
For example:.
Run!
Leave!
Work!
These are the simplest complete sentences
you can make in English; they are just
one.
Word long!
Of course, most sentences are longer than
this.
Most sentences that are longer than one
word also need a noun before the verb.
This noun is the subject.
With a subject plus a verb, you can make
simple sentences :.
He runs.
She left.
They are working.
You can see that the verb can be in
different forms: past or present, simple
or continuous.
The verb form doesn’t change the
structure of the sentence.
These are all the same: subject plus verb.
Of course, these sentences aren’t very
interesting.
You can’t say much with short sentences
these.
Let is add a little more information.
Take the sentence he runs.
What could you add after runs to make it
longer?
You could add an adverb of place:.
He runs around the park.
You could add an adverb of time:.
He runs every morning.
You could add both:.
He runs around the park every morning.
You could add an adverb of manner:.
He runs slowly.
You can see that you have many choices,
but your choices are also limited.
In this case, you can use different kinds
of adverbs, but there are also things you.
Can’t use.
For example, you can’t use another verb
after run, you can’t use an adjective,
and.
You can’t use a noun, or at least you
can’t use a noun with this meaning of run.
This is an important point, let is look
at it in more detail.
To build grammatically complete sentences
in English, there is one important
question:.
What needs to come next?
For example, you saw the sentence he runs.
That is a complete sentence.
You can put a full stop after runs, and
it is correct.
It is very basic, but it is correct.
What about these:.
She likes He wants.
We go.
These aren’t complete sentences.
Can you explain why not?
They aren’t complete, very simply,
because they aren’t finished.
Look at the first sentence: She likes.
She likes…what?
She has to something.
He wants….
What does he want?
You can’t just ‘want’, you have to want
something.
We go….
Where?
At this point, we want to teach you a
word: complement.
The complement is the thing you add after
a verb to make a sentence complete.
A complement can have many different
forms.
It can be a noun, a verb, an adjective or
an adverb.
These things can be single words or
phrases.
For example, when we say ‘noun’, we also
mean noun phrases.
, table is a noun, and the wooden table
which my grandmother gave me is also a
noun.
Both nouns refer to one object—one table.
For this lesson, a noun can be one word,
or a phrase.
, let is practice.
Look at the first sentence: she likes.
How could you finish this?
What are the possible complements?
Pause the video and write down three
endings for your sentence.
Try to use different ideas and structures.
Ready?
Let is look at some possible answers.
These are just our suggestions; of course
there are many possibilities!
She likes strawberries.
She likes swimming.
She likes getting up before the sun rises.
She likes to listen to music while she
works.
You can see that there is more than one
possible complement: you can use a noun,
a gerund (a.
Verb with -ing which acts a noun), a
gerund phrase, or an infinitive verb with.
‘to’.
, you have many choices!
However, before, your choices are also
limited.
Only certain structures are possible.
The idea of complements isn’t just for
the first verb in the sentence.
Many words need a complement.
For example, look at one of the sentences
you just saw:.
She likes getting up before the sun rises.
Technically, you can say She likes
getting up.
It is a grammatically complete sentence,
but you’d never say it.
Why not?
Because it doesn’t make any sense.
You need more information.
She likes getting up… when?
Why?
How?
You need a complement after getting up to
complete the idea.
She likes getting up before….
Before also needs a complement.
You can’t stop there.
Before what?
She likes getting up before the sun….
This also doesn’t work, because it
doesn’t make sense.
It doesn’t make sense because the sun
needs a complement.
Before the sun does what?
She likes getting up before the sun rises.
, finally we have a sentence which is
both grammatically complete and which
communicates.
Meaning.
What should you remember from this?
Remember that when you use a particular
word, you have limited choices in what
word.
You use next.
To speak or write in clear, correct
English, you don’t just need to know
English words.
You need to know what can come next.
For example, with a verb or want, it is
not enough to know the verb.
You also need to know whether the verb
needs a complement, and what complements
are—or?
Aren’t—possible.
This is why it is good to learn
vocabulary in full phrases and sentences.
That way, you’ll know how to use the
words you learn to make sentences you can
use in?
Your spoken or written English.
Using what you’ve seen up to now, you can
build many simple English sentences.
Let is see how you can add more
information and more detail to these
simple sentences.
You can add information to a simple
sentence in two ways: you can add
adjectives or adverbs.
Let is look at an example, using a
sentence we started before, but we didn’t
finish:.
He wants….
, you should do some work!
Pause the video, and finish this sentence
in three different ways.
Start again when you have your answers.
Ready?
Here is our suggestion:.
He wants to buy a car.
Now, let is add some description using
adjectives and adverbs.
Can how you could add adjectives to this
sentence?
You could add adjectives before the word
car, this:.
He wants to buy a new car.
He wants to buy a second-hand car.
He wants to buy a bright red car.
What about adverbs?
Could you add adverbs to these sentences
to add some details?
There are many possibilities; for
example:.
Apparently, he wants to buy a new car.
He wants to buy a second-hand car next
month.
He wants to buy a bright red car for his
new girlfriend.
You can see that adverbs can be single
words or phrases.
Adjectives can go before the noun they
describe, or after some verbs.
Adverbs are more complicated, and can go
in many different positions.
However, this is the important point:
using adjectives and adverbs this doesn’t.
Change whether a sentence is complete or
not.
If you say:.
He wants to buy a car.
That is a complete sentence.
You can add adjectives and adverbs to it
to make it more detailed:.
Apparently, he wants to buy a second-hand
car for his new girlfriend.
However, if a sentence is incomplete,
then you can’t make it complete by adding
adjectives.
Or adverbs:.
He wants to buy….
This sentence is incomplete.
Adding adjectives and adverbs won’t make
it complete.
, at this point, you can build a simple
sentence.
You also hopefully understand something
about complements and why they are
important for?
Making complete sentences, and now you
can also add description to a complete
sentence.
Using adjectives and adverbs.
Let is see how you can combine these
simple sentences into complex ones.
First, let is define some words.
A conjunction is something which joins
two sentences or two parts of a sentence
together.
Words and, but, if, although, because or
which are conjunctions.
A complex sentence contains two or more
parts joined with a conjunction.
These parts are called clauses.
An independent clause expresses a
complete idea, and could stand by itself.
A dependent clause would not make sense
if it were by itself.
A dependent clause depends on an
independent clause in the same sentence
in order to have.
Meaning.
Don’t worry if this is new—you don’t need
to remember everything now.
You’ll see lots of examples of these
ideas in this section and the next
section, too.
In this section, you are going to learn
about complex sentences with two
independent clauses.
, enough abstract talk!
Let is see some examples:.
He runs around the park every morning, he
is in pretty good shape.
She likes strawberries, but she hardly
ever eats them.
You should write to her and thank her for
the present.
These are simple examples of complex
sentences.
Here is your recipe: independent clause +
conjunction + independent clause.
You generally need a comma at the end of
the first clause, before the conjunction,
but.
Comma rules are quite flexible in
English, you won’t always need a comma.
Look at the first example:.
He runs around the park every morning, he
is in pretty good shape.
Which word is the conjunction?
The conjunction is .
You can split this sentence into two
full, meaningful sentences:.
Let is look at one more:.
She likes strawberries, but she hardly
ever eats them.
Again, you can split this into two full
sentences.
You might think that the second sentence.
Here isn’t complete or doesn’t make sense
by itself.
As it is, you’d be .
However, you can change them to
strawberries, and then it is a complete,
meaningful sentence:.
But, she hardly ever eats strawberries.
You can keep adding conjunctions and
clauses for as long as you want:.
She likes strawberries, but she hardly
ever eats them, and she doesn’t earn much
money,.
She has to be careful how much she spends
on groceries, and fresh food is generally?
More expensive than canned or frozen
produce, ….
Of course, just because you can, it
doesn’t mean it is a good idea.
Sentences with too many clauses are
difficult to follow, it is generally
better to limit.
Your complex sentences to two or,
maximum, three clauses.
Now, how to build complex sentences using
independent clauses.
What about dependent clauses?
Do you remember the definition of a
dependent clause?
A dependent clause is a part of a
sentence which would not make sense by
itself.
Let is see an example:.
She is taller than I am.
This short sentence has two clauses.
Can where the two clauses start and end,
and which one is dependent?
The two clauses are:.
She is taller.
And: Than I am.
They are linked with the conjunction than.
The second clause, than I am, is
dependent.
It doesn’t make sense by itself.
Let is see some other ways to build
complex sentences with dependent clauses.
You can add a dependent clause with
conjunctions if, because, although,
unless, or wherever.
For example:.
If you are late, I’ll leave without you.
He is broke because he spent all his
money on beer.
Although she spends a lot of time at
work, she doesn’t get much done.
I won’t do it unless you come with me.
We can meet wherever you want.
Often, you can change the order of the
two clauses if you want, you can say:.
If you are late, I’ll leave without you.
Or: I’ll leave without you if you are
late.
Notice that there is a comma between the
two clauses if the dependent clause is
first,.
But not if the independent clause is
first.
What is the difference between these
complex sentences and the ones you saw in
part four?
Here, you can’t split the sentence in two.
, you can, but one of the two parts won’t
make sense:.
If you are late.
I’ll leave without you.
I’ll leave without you is an independent
clause, it makes sense by itself.
But the other clause—if you are late—is
dependent, and it doesn’t make sense by.
Itself.
It needs something more to make it
complete.
What other common ways are there to build
complex sentences with dependent clauses?
Another common structure is relative
clauses, using relative pronouns who,
which or.
What to link two clauses.
For example:.
That is the guy who shouted at me.
I have no idea what is going on.
They gave us a cake which was made from
dried beetroot.
In these cases, the dependent clause goes
after the independent clause.
Let is review what you’ve learned in this
lesson.
You can build a very simple sentence,
with just a verb:.
Work!
You can add a subject and complement to
make a simple sentence:.
She works in a zoo.
You can use adjectives and adverbs to add
description.
Apparently, she works in a private zoo.
You can make a complex sentence by adding
a second independent clause, with a
conjunction.
Apparently, she works in a private zoo,
she must know a lot about animals.
You can also make a complex sentence by
adding a dependent clause, or even
several dependent.
Clauses, again using conjunctions to
connect them.
Apparently, she works in a private zoo,
she must know a lot about animals, which
surprises.
Me because as far as I know she studied
economics at university, although I guess
I could be.
Wrong.
This is a big topic, and it will take you
time to learn everything about these
points.
Studying conjunctions and how they work
can help you to build complex sentences
which?
Are clear and correct.
Relative clauses are another useful topic
if you want to improve your sentence
grammar.
Learning about relative clauses can help
you to connect your ideas in complex
sentences.
It is also a good idea to study verb
complements and learn what structures you
can or can’t?
Use after a verb.
Remember that a lot of sentence structure
is being able to answer the question:
“What.
Needs to come next?”.
We hope this lesson was useful for you.
Check out our website for more free
English lessons: Oxford Online English
dot com.
Thanks for watching!
See you next time!