hi I'm Brian wilds and in this video I'm
going to explain how to use all 12
tenses in English let's get started as
you might be aware English has four
present tenses and you're probably
familiar with the present simple as in I
study we use this tense when talking
about facts habits and schedules that is
my phone fact he studies every day habit
on weekends we play soccer schedule the
present simple is by far the most common
verb tense in English so you'll get
plenty of practice with this over time
the present continuous I am studying we
use the present continuous to describe
actions that are happening right now as
in you are watching this video right now
I am speaking on camera an airplane is
flying through the sky with this tense
the action is happening as we speak the
present perfect I have studied we use
the present perfect when talking about
how an action from the past describes
the subject now as in I have studied
English for 3 years in this sentence
have studied English is a past action
but we're using it to describe who I am
now it's my experience and we often use
the present perfect to talk about
someone's experience or lack of
experience she has eaten breakfast
already he has lived there all his life
they have never been to Mexico we're
using past experience to describe who
the subject is now and that's why this
is a present tense and finally the
present perfect continuous I have been
studying we use the present perfect
continuous to talk about an action that
started in the past and continues
nonstop into the present I have been
studying Spanish for8 years in other
words I started studying 8 years ago I
never stopped and I'm still learning now
I have been studying we often use this
tense to emphasize when an ongoing
action first started he has been
sleeping for 12 hours she has been
working two jobs since February they
have been traveling for 5
weeks okay ready to talk about the past
let's do it and again we have four
tenses first up is the past simple I
studied this tense is very
straightforward and very common we use
it when talking about an action that
started in the past and finished in the
past for example she worked last night
night in other words she started work
last night and she finished work last
night he ate eggs for breakfast he ate
eggs then he's not eating them now I
lived in Chicago when I was a child I
liveed there then and I don't live there
now why because an action in the past
simple is always finished in the past
great now we have the past continuous I
was studying we use the past continuous
to describe an action that continued
over a period of time in the past I was
studying but more specifically we almost
always use this tense to give context or
background for another action I was
studying when the phone rang we were
living in Canada when we got engaged he
was running when he caught the ball the
past perfect I had studied this tense is
also used to provide context for another
action in the past but the past perfect
always comes beforehand Sarah had
already left by the time he got home in
other words Sarah left before he got
home it could have been a minute before
an hour before or a year before all we
know is she had already left let's look
at two more examples I had already
booked the tickets when the concert sold
out in other words I booked the tickets
before the concert sold out we had eaten
a big lunch so we weren't hungry when we
got to the hotel in other words we ate a
big lunch before we got to the hotel so
we weren't hungry and finally the past
perfect continuous I had been studying
and again we almost always use this
tense to give context but the past
perfect continuous describes an action
that continued over time and then
stopped at the moment of another action
I had been watching TV when the power
went out I was watching I was watching I
was watching power went out no more
watching he had been eating pizza every
day when he started the diet eating
pizza eating pizza eating pizza started
the diet we had been talking about about
going to France for years and finally
decided to go talking about going
talking about going talking about going
decided to go congratulations we've now
covered all the past tenses of English
excellent work we're on to the final
stretch the future and again we've got
four tenses let's begin with the future
simple I will study we use the future
simple to talk about actions that we
believe will happen in the future I will
call you tomorrow we'll bring cupcakes
to the party he'll be there by 6:00 p.m.
and yes most of the time English
speakers shorten the word will to as in
I'll study you'll study he'll study etc
etc and there's another form of the
future simple that you might already be
familiar with going to or gonna as in
I'm going to call you tomorrow we're
going to bring cupcakes to the park he's
going to be there by 6:00 p.m. the will
and going to forms have the same meaning
but going to or GNA is more casual the
future continuous I will be studying we
use the future continuous to talk about
an action that we believe will continue
over a period of time in the future for
example we will be eating dinner from
6:00 to 7:00 p.m. I'll be running
errands all afternoon and again we can
also use going to instead of will
they're going to be traveling all summer
the babies going to be sleeping when you
arrive the future perfect I will have
studied we use the future perfect to
talk about actions that will be finished
by a certain time in the future for
example she will have moved to a new
apartment before the end of the year in
other words here's the end of the year
and she'll move to a new apartment
sometime before that could be a day
before a week before a month before
anytime let's look at two more examples
he will have finished his homework by
the time dinner is ready so dinner is
ready and he finished his homework some
time before that they will have come
home by the spring so spring comes and
they came home sometime before that the
action will be finished before a given
time in the future and finally the
future perfect continuous I will have
been studying so this time we're talking
about a continuous action that will be
completed at a given time in the future
he will have been driving for 6 hours
straight when he arrives now honestly
English speakers rarely use this tense
but when we do it's to emphasize the
duration of an action how long long it
will take we will have been living in
Los Angeles for a decade this December
she will have been working at the
company for 40 years when she retires
and that's it we've covered all 12
tenses of English congratulations if you
have any questions or comments please
let me know and as always thanks for
watching